<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="4508" status="New">
<title>Meaning of "compatible" and C++ desire for C23 changes unclear for `va_arg`</title>
<section><sref ref="[cstdarg.syn]"/></section>
<submitter>Hubert Tong</submitter>
<date>15 Dec 2025</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
The wording in subclause 7.16.1.1 of both C17 and C23 has 
</p>
<blockquote><p>
"[if] type is not compatible with the type of the actual next argument (as promoted according to the default argument promotions) [...]".
</p></blockquote>
<p>
<sref ref="[cstdarg.syn]"/> only clarifies that the default argument promotions are replaced with the C++ version, 
seemingly leaving the C definition of "compatible" as operative for C++ in this context.
<p/>
Consider, for example, the topic of <a href="https://cplusplus.github.io/CWG/issues/3046.html">CWG 3046</a>, 
"Enumerations as part of the common initial sequence": Enumerations with the same underlying type need not 
have equivalent sets of values in C++, whereas C enumerations with the same underlying type are compatible 
and capable of representing the same values. Thus, enumerations should only be defined by C++ as being 
layout-compatible if, in addition to having the same underlying type, they also have equivalent sets of values. 
This difference between C++'s "layout-compatible" types and C's "compatible" types means that we should avoid 
using C's "compatible" in C++ contexts.
<p/>
Furthermore, C23 expanded the bullets.
<p/>
It now reads:
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
[&hellip;] except for the following cases:
</p>
<ul>
<li><p>both types are pointers to qualified or unqualified versions of compatible types;</p></li>
<li><p>one type is compatible with a signed integer type, the other type is compatible with the 
corresponding unsigned integer type, and the value is representable in both types;</p></li>
<li><p>one type is pointer to qualified or unqualified void and the other is a pointer to a 
qualified or unqualified character type;</p></li>
<li><p>or, the type of the next argument is nullptr_t and type is a pointer type that has the 
same representation and alignment requirements as a pointer to a character type.</p></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>
Assuming that "compatible" is read as "layout-compatible", the first bullet, whose effect in C is 
to allow limited differences in qualification, allows further differences in the pointee types in 
C++ because pointers are not layout-compatible in C++ when the pointee types are layout-compatible 
but not the same type.
<p/>
Clearer wording, likely with more restrictions than C, is needed. A question, though, is whether 
"compatible" should generally be replaced (for `va_arg`) with "layout-compatible" or a requirement 
for being the same type. In the specific case of the first bullet, I believe the latter is the right choice.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
